Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin
1779 December-1780 December
Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1077 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Scope and Contents note
    Arrival of the schooner called the "Committee" from Boston; news of Count d'Estaing being in Georgia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 1; L.S. 3p.; Gillon, Alexander. Frankfort-on-the-Main
    Concerning the purchase and fitting out of two large ships, built at Amsterdam; believes with Franklin's aid, Capt. Jones's skill and his own assiduity that there is a fair prospect of their procuring a fleet for America; his disinterested devotion to that country; begs Franklin to take him by the hand and steer him through this difficulty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Mesmer, Friederich Anton. Paris
    As Franklin has shown an interest in the advantages arising from the discovery of animal magnetism, hopes that he will satisfy himself of the genuineness of certain cures he has made; besides the cases that Franklin has already seen, has several others which he will show him on the following Wednesday, if he will dine with him on that day.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume
    Begging for the return of M. Nairne's memoir on the apparatus designed for storing electricity. Impossible to procure another copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Conyngham, Gustavus. Texel
    Account of his barbarous treatment by the English during his captivity; unhappy situation of the unfortunate prisoners in Plymouth; afraid they will be obliged to enter the English service unless they are soon exchanged.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 348.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Rousseaux, Jean. Wakefield
    Begging Franklin to procure his exchange and release him from his present condition of slavery.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Mitchell, George. Brittany
    Repeating his former request that he may be set at liberty and suffered to return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 2; L.S. 2p.; Penet, D'Acosta frères and Cie. Nantes
    Enclosing two letters just arrived from Philadelphia; one for Franklin and one for M. Le Ray de Chaumont.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 3; L.S. 3p.; Famin, Jean-Baptiste. Paris
    General belief that Spain will acknowledge America's independence, with the result of establishing consulships in her different ports. Desires the position of Consul at Barcelona.
    (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 3; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Watelet, Claude Henri. Paris
    Desiring to know if Franklin will receive the Commander of the King's frigate "l'Oiscau"; he is anxious to consult with him on a matter of some interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    News received of the arrival at Savannah of a detachment from Comte d'Estaing's fleet, who took and destroyed the British armed vessels on the coast and made prisoners of eight hundred soldiers at Beaufort.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Copy of a certificate by Harmen Fleus, pilot, stating that on November 28th Vice Admiral Reynst ordered the ship "Alliance" to go to sea when wind and weather rendered it both dangerous and impossible then and since November 23d; orders from Admiral Reynst have exceeded both the intention and terms of the last Resolution.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 5; A.L.S. 1p.; de Beaumont, Santerre. Magny
    Franklin reported to have claimed his descent from a notary of Pontoise named Dagneaux; is in a position to procure the genealogy of this family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 5; A.L.S. 8p.; Charles Carroll of Carrollton. Annapolis
    Introducing Mr. Thomas Ridout. Acknowledges his favor of June 20th by the Chevalier de la Luzerne. Reasons why he resigned his seat in Congress. Deplorable state of the public credit; heavy taxation recommended by Congress. Exorbitant price of all provisions; measures suggested by Congress to check this evil. Describes the army as consisting of 20,000 fine, hardy fellows, well disciplined, well armed, and pretty tolerably clothed, but not strong enough to drive the English out of New York. Sketches a plan of operation which he believes would result in bringing the war to a speedy issue.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Jenings, Edmund. Brussels
    Sends a copy of the King's speech to Parliament. Will be pleased to receive Franklin's commands; ambitious to serve his country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 6; A.L.S. 4p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Acknowledging the two commissions for the "Black Prince" and "Princess." Aid given to Mr. Wharton and Mr. de Chaumont in their mission. If Capt. Conyngham comes to Dunkirk will give him Franklin's letter and furnish him with the necessary funds. Sorry that Franklin has been troubled with complaints from some of the people of the "Black Prince"; gives an impartial opinion on the subject. Encloses two letters for Franklin from Jonathan Arnold, late lieutenant of the "Black Prince," who made his escape from prison with Capt. Conyngham.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Patrick Dowlin and others. Dunkirk
    A warm denial of the charges brought by William Power and his gang against their worthy friend, Mr. John Torris; his generous behavior to every individual of the crew of the "Black Prince."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Rotterdam
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of August 6th concerning a first draft of the United States, drawn on Franklin for $30, and presented for payment; precautionary measures they have taken in case of forgery.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Norway, Richard
    Wishes to serve the American cause; must conceal his true name until he receives an answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Vindicating himself of charges brought by certain prisoners, headed by one William Power, who first swore allegiance to the United States and now refuses to serve except under the English flag; Mr. Coffyn and all honest citizens know his probity and no one has just cause to complain of him for the armament of the "Black Prince."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 8; L.S. 1p.; Beaumarchais, Pierre-Augustin Caron de. Paris
    Has heard that Franklin intends taking a hotel in Paris, and consequently will need the services of a porter; recommends a man called Abbey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Ferrol
    Congress having appointed him to a new mission in Europe, embarked on November 13th, but his vessel having sprung a formidable leak, was obliged to anchor at Ferrol. Is the bearer of despatches from Congress and some newspapers containing an account of the evacuation of Rhode Island by the enemy, and of the Comte d'Estaing's progress in Georgia. Hopes the "Confederacy" arrived safely with M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gé [de Rayneval] and Mr. Jay, who is appointed Minister Plenipotentiary to Spain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Villiers, Louis-Pierre Dufourny de
    Wishing to know the value of a quantity of American paper money. Concerning the session of the "Assemblé publique de la Faculteé,"and the effort that will be made to reconcile them with the "Société Royale de Médecine." Report of Count d'Estaing's feats in Georgia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Business with M. Mercier; sending paper money and receipts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, Henry. Paris
    Mr. Moses Grinnell's misfortunes; measures to help him recover the lost bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 9; A.L.S 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Doubtful whether Commodore Jones's squadron sailed or not.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 9; L.S. 2p.; Bubier, Christopher et al. Coutances
    Six Americans who escaped from Mill prison in England and who were arrested on suspicion on landing in France, petition Franklin to obtain their release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Sweaney, John. Angers Prison
    Made his escape from an English prison only to be put in a French jail; begs to be released and enabled to return to his family in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Difficulties in the way of obtaining the condemnation of the prize goods taken by the "Mifflin"; begs Franklin to obtain the necessary papers. Saw in an American paper an address to the people of Ireland, signed with Franklin's name; wishes to know if it is genuine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Freeman, William. Bristol
    Writes on behalf of Mr. George Phillips, who was taken prisoner by the French; desires a passport to enable him to return to England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Commines, Gaston de. Filippine
    Has a new invention, which is a great improvement on the usual musketry fire; desires Franklin's assistance in making it known.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridout, T. Annapolis, Md
    Introducing his brother who is about to proceed to Boulogne to transact some business with Mrs. Ogle, a sister of Franklin's old friend, Colonel [Benjamin] Tasker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 12; L. 1p.; L'Air de Lamotte, Jean. Paris
    Condition of M. Dubourg very critical; fears the worst result.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Alliance," Texel
    Has received Franklin's orders of the 6th inst., respecting the prisoners on board the "Alliance"; hopes that his enclosed letter to the Duke de la Vauguyon will meet with Franklin's approbation; persuaded that Franklin would never wish him to be made the tool of any great King; rejected their dirty piece of parchment; they would have him do that which would render him contemptible even in the eyes of his own servants. Will sail as soon as the wind permits.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Intelligence received from. Georgia, disappointing; thinks the English are too much weakened to attempt anything material against the Southern States; letters from Boston of October 28th give an account of the attack on Savannah, the departure of the French fleet, the evacuation of Rhode Island by the English, and the occupation of Newport by Gen. Gates. Eight American prisoners in Bordeaux, captured on board English ships; encloses a letter (2 p.) from one of these (James Jimis) whose case calls for redress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, Alexander John. Passy
    Enclosing two memoirs, which he begs Franklin to deliver to M. de Sartine and M. de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Contrary winds preventing the Commodore's departure. Illness of Mr. Sayre.
  - to [Edward Bancroft], 1779 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    By desire of Commodore Jones, sends him cypher [2 p.] to be used in their correspondence. Hears Mr. William Lee is in town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 15; Printed. N. 1p.; De Lamotte, Lair. Paris
    Invitation to the funcral of M. Barbeu Dubourg.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of Philip Mazzei from Ireland, after being captured on his passage from Virginia and imprisoned by the enemy; claims that he is charged with public business of an important nature on which he is ordered to consult with Franklin; will show him every attention if it is Franklin's wish; favorable impression made on him by Mr. Mazzei.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 16; A.L.S. 9p.; Beccaria, Giambatista. Turin
    Speaks of Franklin's work on the "Aurora Borealis"; has written upon this subject himself; sends a list of his various scientific works, with notes of their contents; hopes they may prove of some service and interest to Franklin.
    (In Italian.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosures by Paul Jones [3p.] relative to pensioning an English pilot. John Jackson, who was forced by accident into the service of the United States, in which service he lost his arm. Copies of letters from Admiral Reynst,. the Chevalier de Lironcourt and Commondore Jones [4p.] relative to Jones leaving the Dutch port at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Chautel,-----. Turin
    Enclosing Père Beccaria's answer [XVI, 165] to Franklin's letter, and offering to act as a medium for any further correspondence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Enclosing the two bonds respecting the privateers, "Black Prince," Capt. Patrick Dowlin, and the "Black Princess," Capt. Edw. Macatter also copies of the oath of allegiance to the United States, administered to the commanders, officers, and crews of said privateers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing account of General Sullivan's successes against the Indians and Tories.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Admiral Reynst's demand that Jones should either fly the French flag or leave the port; reasons in favor of Jones's determination to fly the American colors. Business with M. de. Neufville. Capt. Conyngham on board the "Alliance," as a passenger. Capt. [Richard] Pearson [of H. M. S. "Serapis"] on parole; his sword returned to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 22; The Dean, Canons and Chapter of The Church of Paris
    Invitation to a service in memory of the Archbishop of Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; J.F. Frin and Co. Paris
    Enclosing a letter (2p.) from their friends, Mr. Daniel Crommelin and Son, relative to the payment of certain bills of exchange, with a plan for facilitating such intercourse with Holland in future.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartwell, John. Boulogne Prison
    Born in Boston; was in the English service, but escaped, only to be taken prisoner by the French; begs for his freedom and a pass to enable him to go on board a cutter now at Calais; willing and anxious to fight for his country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 24; L.S. 2p.; Merry, Anthony. Queen Square, Westminster
    Reminding Franklin of the many convivial hours they spent together in Cornhill and Queen Square. Begs that the enclosed, unsealed letter may be forwarded to Capt. Hawker, a worthy officer of His Majesty's 62d regiment of foot, who has been a prisoner in America ever since the convention of Saratoga; desires Franklin's influence to obtain his exchange, as well as that of Major Harnage, as these two are such friends that one will never accept of a release, unless it extends to the other; their miserable and destitute situation. All their old friends at the George and Vulture are alive and well.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Naghel, -----. Paris
    Is engaged in fitting out two armed frigates with supplies for America; desires to know what objects the Colonists particularly need, and what are the best ports for the sale of his cargo and the purchase of a fresh one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 24; A.L.S. 3p.; de Mayz, -----. Paris
    Wishes a position in the American army; his father a well-known Prussian general.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Announcing the birth of his son, who is to be named George; after his dear friend, General Washington; begs Franklin to inform Mr. William Franklin and Dr. Bancroft of the event.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Deane, Silas. Williamsburg, Va
    Hopes to embark for France in the course of two or three weeks. Alarm felt by the accounts from New York of an invasion of Virginia and the other Southern States, which are not well prepared to oppose them; relies much on the severity of the weather to prevent this expedition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of the frigate, "Sensible," in Spain; report that Mr. Adams is on board with credentials as Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of London; desires to know if this extraordinary piece of intelligence is true. Would never solicit public employment, but would be highly gratified to be taken notice of by Congress. Order from M. de Chaumont for clothing for 15,000 men.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Muhlenberg, Henry. Philadelphia
    Writes on behalf of the United German Lutheran Ministers to beg Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to His Prussian Majesty's Ambassador or Secretary, to be conveyed in their turn to Hall in Saxony.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Montgomery, Robert.
    A Minister to the Court of Madrid will probably arrive soon; offers to give orders to his banker to furnish him with whatever money be may need during his residence at Court, if Franklin desires it. Hopes it is not true that Comte d'Estaing has been repulsed with loss in an attack Savannah. The blockade of Gibraltar still continues.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Girault, -----. Paris
    Writes at the request of a commerical house at Rouen to find out if Franklin intends appointing a Consul at that place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Has just received Surgeon Boutey's petition to Franklin; cannot furnish him with his full share of the prize money for some weeks. Sailing of the "Black Prince" and "Princess" on the 21st inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Lamarque, Fabre and Co. Paris
    Enclosing a bill of exchange for acceptance. Offers their services to supply the American troops with uniforms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Prices at which he can procure uniforms, etc., for the soldiers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 before Jan. 1] December 28; L. 1p.; Boulainvilliers, Mme de
    Informing Franklin of the approaching marriage of her daughter to Vicomte de Tonnerre. Hopes Franklin will pray for their happiness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Paul, -----. Paris
    Sure that Franklin will applaud the design of honoring virtue in the person of Jean Jacques Rousseau, of Geneva; encloses the prospectus and begs Franklin to add his name to the list of those who wish to erect a monument to glory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Lee, Henry. Cadiz
    Begs Franklin to write to the Spanish Consul on his behalf; came to Spain as second Captain of a brig from Philadelphia; got into trouble through a dishonest custom's house official; thrown into prison, where he has languished for nine weeks; implores assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 30; L.S. 8p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Paris
    Never received a copy of Capt. Jone's letter to Franklin dated October 3d, until December 15th; answers one by one the four general charges laid against him: (1) Disobedience of orders; (2) firing upon the "Bonhomme Richard"; (3) not having assisted the "Bonhomme Richard" as soon as possible; (4) not going in pursuit of the fleet the next day.
  - to Henrey Coder (with Coder Note to Franklin), 1779 December 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Dubois-Martin, Guy-Martin
    Introducing M. Girault, who desires to recommend a firm at Rouen, in case Franklin intends appointing a Consul at that place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May [4]; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a further declaration by Amsterdam on the subject of the Resolution of November 17th relative to Paul Jones [3p.]. Account of a stormy quarrel between the Grand Facteur and himself. Copy of letter from Paul Jones [1p.] about some small matters on the "Alliance."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 31; A.L.S. 4p.; Barry, Amelia. Leghorn
    Heard only a few days before of the death of her revered god-mamma. Is most grateful for Franklin's generosity in regard to the profits from the sale of Gov. Pownall's new edition of her father's map; hopes therewith to educate her four children. Asks for Franklin's literary works with his inscription, "Gift to My Dear Child," on the title page.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 -----; A.L.S. 1p.; St Esprit, Abbesse Marie du
    Their admiration and respect for Franklin and their prayers for his preservation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 16; L.S. 2p.; Mazzei, Philip. Nantes
    Appointed agent in January, 1779, for the Governor and Council of Virginia. On account of delay in remittances, used his own funds and borrowed more; now, Messrs. D'Acosta, of Nantes, refuse to make him adequate advances on his letter of credit; begs Franklin's advice in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 December 3; Mem. 13p.; Messrs. Famin, Devoize and Cie. Paris
    Propose to establish an improved distillery for brandy, liquors, etc., in Catalonia, Spain, and describe their plan. Jean Baptiste Famin applies for the appointment of Consul for the United States at Barcelona.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard
    Sends this letter by M. Gérard; his popularity in Philadelphia; affection they all have for him. Sends furs and newspapers.
    (First part missing.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Letter just received from Mr. Ridley in Maryland; news of Mr. John Adams being appointed to return to Europe and assist in any future treaty of peace; Mr. [John] Laurens appointed Secretary of Embassy at the French Court.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 May on or After 4]; A.L.S. 3p.; Beckwith, Major-General John
    The misfortunes of the American troops due principally to want of discipline, and perhaps of vigilance and experience in their commanders; where Gen. Washington has commanded in person things have never gone very ill, but he cannot be everywhere. Offers his services to assist in training the troops.
    [Dr. Franklin's answer, dated May 17, 1779, is printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 348, Bigelow, VI, 387, Smyth, VII, 315).]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779]; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Badger, Jno.
    Laying claim to certain lands in Pennsylvania purchased by his mother's brother, Izaac Maritt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bertier, Père Joseph Etienne
    Presenting his respects to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 After Oct. 28; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Bethman, ------
    Will call again on Dr. Franklin and Mr. Adams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1779; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Beaugeard, -----
    Inviting Franklin and his grandson to dine with him on March 28th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Informing Franklin and his grandson that they are invited to dine at Mme. Watelets'.